Society for Industrial Microbiology records
Society for Industrial Microbiology records
1949-2001
1949 2001
Coll015
Society for Industrial Microbiology (U.S.)
51 boxes (26.5 linear feet)
51 boxes
26.5 linear feet
Records document the founding and growth of the Society for Industrial Microbiology. Documents show the development of important society activities such as the Summer Institute, the Education Committee and Awards and Grants Committee, annual meetings and publications such as the SIM Newsletter. They include the officers’ correspondence, financial audits and reports, minutes, memoranda, membership lists, meeting materials, committee reports, and photographs. Also includes publications such as the Society of Industrial Microbiology Newsletter, the Society of Industrial Microbiology News, Developments in industrial microbiology, and the Journal of Industrial Microbiology.
University of Maryland, Baltimore County Albin O. Kuhn Library and Gallery UMBC 1000 Hilltop Circle Baltimore, MD 21250 410-455-2353 speccoll@umbc.edu
This collection of records of the Society for Industrial Microbiology covers the years 1949 – 2001 and includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, financial reports, audits and budgets, constitutions and by-laws, incorporation documents, ledgers, membership lists and directories, brochures, photographs, publications and other records of activities. Documents are arranged into series based on the administrative organization set forth in the society’s policy manual.
Series one, Board of Directors contains the records generated by the President, Vice-President, Secretary and Treasurer arranged by creating officer. Files of the President include correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, beginning with the origin of the Society. Presidential correspondence covers the wide range of activities and interests of the society including committee assignments, awards issues and other administrative concerns. There is only one folder of Vice-Presidential material from 1975-1976. Among the Secretary’s files are the agendas and minutes of the board of directors meetings for 1954, and from 1960 through 1992 inclusive. Files also include correspondence pertaining to administrative activities such as elections, mailing list approvals, business calendars, the certificate of incorporation, constitution, by-laws and revisions, and rosters of officers and committee members. The bulk of the financial records falls under the Treasurer. Along with correspondence files dating as early as 1949 are audit reports, budgets, finance committee reports and ledgers for cash assets, income and disbursements, and receipts.
The second series, Business Secretary, is arranged into two series: Business Office and Membership. The sub-series Business Office contains correspondence, income and expense statements for a variety of Society activities and the Policy Manuals. All documents of the Business Secretary, whether the office was in a private home and or after the National Office was established, are organized together by subject and then in date order. All membership records (which became the responsibility of the Business Secretary after the creation of that position) are together and organized first by subject and then in date order. The sub-series includes applications from 1957, brochures, member lists and printed directories.
The third series, Committees, contains correspondence, memos, reports and rosters of many of the Society committees among them the Archives Committee, the Awards and Grants Committee, the Education Committee and the Summer Institute Committee. The materials show the extent of the interests of the society and the development of their activities. For example, the Summer Institute Committee files outline the inception of the Summer Institute courses and contain materials on courses taught from 1965 – 1970.
Series four, Meetings, contains correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, forms, proceedings, and photographs. There is a block of correspondence from 1960 pertaining to a conference and some related to the Summer Institute dated 1968 – 1971. There is not a complete record of annual meetings and copies of minutes are extent only for the years 1950 – 1985. There is a smattering of reports from the annual meetings running from 1960 –1981 and some photographs from 1981 – 1990. There is a variety of proceedings, programs, papers and reports from workshops, symposia, conferences and joint meetings organized by the society. Of these a few are from 1960 – 1961, with the bulk of the papers coming from the 1980’s and early 1990’s. Also included are records from local chapter meetings. These contain the correspondence, memos, agendas, minutes and reports of five of the local chapters. The earliest of these is the Washington chapter with papers dating from 1951 – 1960, followed by Chicago with papers beginning in 1959 and extending to 1973. The remaining materials date from the 1970’s – 1990. These give a brief look at the workings of local units.
The series Publications is made up primarily of printed works published by the Society. These include a nearly complete run of the SIM Newsletter, runs of both society journals, copies of meeting programs and abstracts, conference papers, and various special publications. In addition, there is a smattering of documents such as contract agreements with the society publisher from the period 1959 – 1962 and some correspondence from the editor of the society newsletter dating from the mid sixties to the late seventies.
In the final series, Affiliated Organizations and Ephemera, are a small number of files relating to other affiliated societies and the records documenting the relationship between SIM and Northwestern University, where the SIM archive had been previously housed and maintained.
Today, within the scientific community, there is a general recognition of the balance and interdependence that exists between the theoretical and the applied sciences. This was not the case in the 1940’s when a growing group of industrial microbiologists began to feel that the practical and industrial aspects of bacteriology were being neglected by the established societies and that there was a need for a forum in which they could present their views and papers.
In the late Summer and early Fall of 1949 Dr. Walter Ezekiel began mailing letters to prospective members concerning the possible formation of a new organization which would support the work of industrial and applied microbiology. The new scientific body he proposed was a Society for Industrial Microbiology. Dr. Ezekiel mentioned his plan to Dr. Raymond L. Taylor, then associate administrative secretary of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) in charge of meetings and programs during a phone conversation in late October. This resulted in the scheduling of an organizational meeting to be held during the upcoming AAAS meetings in New York. At that time, it was decided that a new society, the Society for Industrial Microbiology (SIM) be established as a national scientific organization covering “the field of microbiologic work as applied to industrial materials and processes”.
The first organizational meeting was held in the ballroom of the Hotel McAlpin in New York City on December 29, 1949 with some 300 people in attendance. This new society was to be associated with then newly formed American Institute of Biological Sciences. At that time, Dr. Charles Thom was elected Acting Chairman and C.L. Porter was elected Acting Secretary and Dr. Thom appointed an organizational committee that met several times during the first year to prepare a program for the first annual meeting and to write a constitution.
The first annual meeting was held in conjunction with the American Institute of Biological Sciences (AIBS) on September 11 – 13 1950 at Ohio State in Columbus, Ohio. Thereafter the newly formed society held all its meetings in conjunction with the AIBS meetings. It was not until 1967 that they began to hold independent annual meetings. The first of these was held at the University of Western Ontario in London, Ontario Canada. In 1960 the Society for Industrial Microbiology was incorporated in the District of Columbia.
From the original 300 members SIM membership grew to about 550 in 1959. In that year the SIM began offering corporate membership in the society. By 1975 the society had grown to the point where it had approximately 1000 members including some 46 corporate members. Due to the significant growth in the society a position of Business Secretary was established in 1973 to assist the society in managing its expanding activities. In addition, Local Sections were being established in different parts of the country.
At present, SIM still has well under 2,000 members. This is no accident. At the outset the society wanted to foster a climate where the rank and file would know each other on a first name basis. In fact, C. L. Porter stated in a presidential address that “a membership of more than 1,200 – 1,500 should be discouraged for then we like other groups mentioned, would lose the personal contact which was one of the principal attractions.”
Over the years, SIM has made use of publications to give recognition for research in the practical aspects of microbiology and to announce scientific findings. As early as 1951, SIM put out its first publication, the SIM News Letter (changed to SIM News in November 1972) followed by the publication of its first journal Applied Microbiology in 1953. This served as the official publication of SIM until 1960 when the second journal to be published by the society, Developments in Industrial Microbiology, became the official publication of SIM. In 1963, SIM began publishing their Special Publications series that would later included proceedings or lectures of the Summer Institute. In 1986, the Journal of Industrial Microbiology (now the Journal of Industrial Microbiology & Biotechnology) was launched to be a companion to the earlier Developments in Industrial Microbiology. By 1964 SIM began to turn its attention to the problem of education. It was decided that SIM should begin a series of summer courses designed to focus on specific areas of interest as well as “practical methods” and that these courses should promote the enrollment of technician level employees of firms conducting microbiological work. The courses were to be open to all college graduates and that SIM membership would not be required. In 1965 the first of the Summer Institute courses, an Introduction to Genetics, was held at the University of Minnesota.
In addition, over the years SIM has established numerous awards. The first award, the Certificate of Merit (now the C.L. Porter Award for Distinguished Service) was created in 1963 to recognize individual members for unselfish and outstanding service to the society. A second award the SIM High School Science Award was established in 1964. In 1966 the Charles H. Thom Award, the highest award in the society was instituted to award individuals who have made outstanding contributions to research in industrial microbiology. The first recipient of this award was Kenneth B. Raper in August of 1967. Since those early years several more awards have been created to recognize the outstanding work in the field. The Waksman Outstanding Teaching Award was established in 1989 and in 1992 the Schering-Plough Research Institute Young Investigator Award intended to give recognition and support young researchers was instituted.
In 2011, the organization changed its name to the Society for Industrial Microbiology and Biotechnology (SIMB). The National Office currently resides in Fairfax, Virginia.
Organized in six series: Series I. Board of Directors, 1949-2000. Series II. Business Secretary, 1949-1999. Series III. Committees, 1952-1996. Series IV. Meetings, 1949-2001. Series V. Publications, 1951-2000. Series VI. Affiliated Organizations and Ephemera, 1967-1989.
Series I. Board of Directors
President
Vice President
Secretary
Treasurer
Series II. Business Secretary
Business Office
Membership
Series III. Committees
Series IV. Meetings
Correspondence
Annual Meetings
Conferences, Symposia, & Workshops
Joint Meetings
Local Chapter Meetings
Series V. Publications
Journals and Newsletters
Conferences, Workshops, & Meeting Materials
Special Publications and Miscellanea
Series VI. Affiliated Organizations and Ephemera
No restrictions.
Finding aid available.
SARCV 2000-11; SARCV 2001-06; SARCV 2002-04. This collection was received in three accessions. The first accession of 20 cubic feet of records arrived from Northwestern University on August 28, 2000; the second accession of 8 cubic feet was sent directly from the SIM office in Fairfax, VA and arrived on October 25, 2001; and the third, comprising one folder, was delivered by Dr. Joan Bennett on Dec 13, 2002.
Society for Industrial Microbiology (U.S.) Archives; Industrial microbiology Societies, etc.
Society for Industrial Microbiology and Biotechnology. Accessed November 13, 2015.
- Series I. Board of Directors, 1949-2000; bulk 1960-1991; 6,250 items; (9 linear feet)
  Correspondence, minutes, reports, audits, budgets, tax and insurance forms, ledgers, constitutions and by-laws, rosters, business calendars, and certificates of incorporation arranged into four sub-series: President, Vice President, Secretary, and Treasurer.
  - Subseries I.A. President, 1949-1996; 1,300 items; (1.75 linear feet)
    General correspondence and memos arranged in date order followed by subject files in alphabetical order.
    - Correspondence 1949/12 – 1953/4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1959/5 – 1960/8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1960/9 – 1961/7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence 1962/3-1967/7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence 1967/8-1969/12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1970/1-1971/12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence 1972/2-1973/12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence 1974/5-1975/10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence 1975/9-1976/3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence 1976/4-1976/11 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1977/8-1977/12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1978/1-1978/7 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence 1987/7-12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1988/1-1988/6 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence 1988/7-1988/9 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence 1989/1-1989/4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1988/10-1988/12 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1989/5-9 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence 1989/1-1990/9 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence Annual Letters 1960-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence Committees 1989/1-5 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence Committees 1989/6-1989/9 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Corporate Members 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence ONR Lecture 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Paula Keith 1987-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Subseries I.B. Vice President, 1975-1976; 4 items; (1 folder)
    - Correspondence 1975/10-1976/10 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.C. Secretary, 1949-1992; bulk 1960-1990; 3,100 items (3.5 linear feet)
    Correspondence, Board of Directors minutes, reports, constitutions and by-laws, business calendars, and certificate of incorporation organized first by subject and then in date order.
    - Correspondence 1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1985-1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Committee on the Deterioration of Fuels 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence Elections 1962-1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence Emeritus Members 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence Mailing List Approvals 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence Mailing List Approvals 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence Special Publications 1963-1983 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Account Record 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Business Calendar 1977-1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Business Calendar 1983-1990 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Certificate of Incorporation (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - By Laws, Constitution and Revisions (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Rosters 1949-1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1954 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1961 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1962 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1966 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1968 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1969 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports (Part I) 1975 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports (Part II) 1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports (Part I) 1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports (Part II) 1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1977 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1978 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1980 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1980 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports (Part I) 1982 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports (Part II) 1982 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1983 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1983 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1984, March (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1984/8 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1984/11 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1986 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1987/4 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1987/8 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1988/2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1988/8 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1988/12 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1989 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1990 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes and Reports 1991-1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Subseries I.D. Treasurer, 1949-2000; 2,175 items (3.75 linear feet)
    Correspondence, audit and financial reports, budgets, tax and insurance forms, and ledgers arranged in order by subject and then in date order.
    - Correspondence 1949-1964 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1965 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence 1966 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence 1967 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1968 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence 1969 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence 1970 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence 1971 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence 1974 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence 1974 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence 1980 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence 1980-1982 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: IRS/Buoman’s Secretary 1974-1993 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: Legal Matters 1975-1978 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Audit Reports 1963-1969 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Audit Reports 1970-1975 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Audit Reports 1976-1979 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Audit Reports 1979-1983 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Audit Reports 1980-1984 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Audit Reports 1985-1989 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Audit Reports 1994-2000 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Annual Meeting Income and Expenses 1974-1984 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Budgets 1967-1978 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Budgets 1980-1985 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Checking Account Register 1966, 1978, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Exempt from Income Tax Forms 1964-1983 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Insurance Policies 1971-1983 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Finance Committee 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Committee Lists and Budgets 1988-1989 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Ledger/Development in Industrial Micro-Biology 1972-1978 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Ledger/Income and Disbursements 1972-1973, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Ledger 1980-1981 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Ledger Cash Assets 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Ledger Cash Receipts and Disbursements 1982-1984 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Ledger Cash Receipts 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Ledger Income and Disbursements for Annual Meeting 1988 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Ledger Adjusting Entries 1989/3 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Ledger Income Statement Printouts 1989 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Ledger Trial Balance 1988/11-1989/6 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Publishers: Developments in Industrial Micro-Biology Sales Reports 1964-1975 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Reports 1975-1979,1984 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Reports 1965-1974 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Series II. Business Secretary, 1949-1999; bulk 1950-1996; 1,400 items (2.75 linear feet)
  Correspondence, memos, reports, applications, ledgers, member lists and directories, and policy manuals arranged into two sub-series: Business Office and Membership.
  - Subseries II.A. Business Office, 1973-1985; 200 items (.25 linear feet)
    Correspondence, memos, contracts, income and expense statements, and policy manuals organized by subject and then arranged in date order.
    - Correspondence, Memos, and Reports 1973-1985 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Contract of Employment 1975 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Income and Expense Statements, Annual Meeting 1981 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Income and Expense Statements, Annual Meeting 1982 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Income and Expense Statements, Annual Meeting 1983 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Income and Expense Statements, Membership 1981-1983 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Income and Expense Statements, Office Expenses 1983 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Income and Expense Statements, Publications 1981 - 1984 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Income and Expense Statements, Misc. N/D (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Policy Manuel 1972 (Box 18, Folder 1)